[Music]
[Applause]
mind muscle connection take one which is
more important for muscle growth
Progressive overload or the Mind muscle
connection so to my knowledge there's no
research investigating this question so
this is purely theoretical but I'm
pretty confident in my answer I always
use this hypothetical twin example to
illustrate the point you let's say a
pair of Twins start lifting weights both
of them weigh 200 lb just to make it
easy you know and they're both 20% body
fat okay so twin number one he focuses
on the Mind muscle connection he does
this for two years so every exercise he
does he's just squeezing and you know
using super good form squeezing the
weight pausing at the top of the
contraction and lowering under control
and the other twin instead focuses on
getting stronger setting PRS and he does
that for 2 years at the end of this time
period you know at the end of two years
let's say they had the same routine they
did the same exercises the only thing
that was different is how they perform
the exercise and then their focus would
obviously dictate the loading you know
that they used so twin one would
obviously be going lighter and wouldn't
be so focused on always going up in
strength whereas twin number two would
only be focused on going up in reps or
weight over time but let's say they
mostly did compound movements you know
they did bench press you know incline
press military press dips chinups pull
Downs rows squats lunges deadlifts hip
thrusts and let's say they still threw
in a little bit of leg extensions and
leg curls and kickbacks and 45° hypers
you know lateral raises some flies some
lap prayers rear delt raises some curls
and tricep extensions but say 70% of
their volume was compound movements 30%
single joint my guess is that at the end
of the 2 years period you know let's say
they had the same diet they they they
got their protein in they had around a
gram per pound of body weight per day at
the end of this 2-year period my guess
is that twin two would be more muscular
than twin number one my guess is that
twin number one now might be you know
200 lb and say 15% body fat but twin two
would be 200 lb and you know like 10 to
12% body fat now let me first make a
case for the Mind muscle connection so
around 10 years ago this big debate in
the industry started you know what's
best for strength and muscle hypertrophy
what type of cues should trainers and
coaches use when working with their
clients or athletes should they use an
internal Focus attention or an external
focus of attention and what that means
is an internal focus of attention you're
focusing on your body something within
your body whereas an external Focus has
you focusing on something outside the
body some Target or you know something
in the environment and there are so many
studies there's like you know over a
hundred studies looking at performance
and with regards to Performance an
external attentional focus is always
better you know it always rains Supreme
if you want more Force production
someone's doing a bench press you're not
going to be like okay I want you to
really feel your triceps doing the job
you're going to say explode up you know
I want you to blast that weight off your
chest fight through the sticking region
and envision yourself throwing that bar
through the ceiling say you're doing a
broad jump you're not going to be like
all right Lean Forward I want you to
really feel your glutes explode and
Propel you forward no instead you're
going to say look see this distance
right here Pretend This is a fire pit
you got to clear that or you're going to
die I want you jumping to right there
you're going to give them a Target and
they're going to focus on that and they
might beat that Target you know even if
it's like accuracy if se's throwing a
dart you're not going to tell them you
know how to contract their tricep
that'll just throw them off you're going
to instead give them some environmental
cue like you're going to say ignore the
big dart board you know the whole circle
I want you to only focus on that little
bullseye area throw it right there so
anything performance related whether
it's strength or force or power and
speed or accuracy you know putting a
golf ball throwing a dart in all those
scenarios an external attentional focus
is superior to an internal attentional
Focus so 10 years ago the whole industry
was saying oh external cues are always
better than internal cues for everything
and I'm pretty proud of myself cuz back
then I said no you know there are times
when internal attentional focus is valid
for example with hypertrophy fixing form
so I made a chart and there was some
industry guys who got upset at me
because they were so tied to this
external attentional Focus you know they
weren't being objective and I made this
chart that said yes for anything
performance related external but for
basically hypertrophy and fixing form
like if you want someone to not cave in
at the knees you just say knees out you
know don't let your knees cave in push
your knees out and then you do a better
job with your form sometimes you need to
draw lifter's attention to something
going on within his body but there was
no research looking into this until my
friend Brad shonfeld I was on this paper
he conducted a study that looked at
whether or not an external or internal
attentional Focus was Superior for
hypertrophy and he looked at curls and
leg extensions now the quads did not
show uh superiority for the internal CU
but the biceps did the group that
focused on the biceps Contracting saw
better results than the group that just
focused on the load being moved so chalk
went up for the minor muscle connection
that's the first and only paper to my
knowledge looking at the effects of
attentional focus on hypertrophy however
prior to that there were probably I'd
say 10 studies involving muscle
activation showing that when you do
focus on the muscle you do activate that
muscle to a greater degree so for
example if you are doing a glute bridge
and you focus on squeezing your glutes
you're going to use your glutes more and
there's some evidence that suggest that
you end up using other muscles less and
I did my own experiments back in the day
and I found that experienced lifters
could kind of steer their muscle
activity towards one muscle group over
another you know you could squat using
your quads and not so much your glutes
or vice versa and when you focused on
using a certain muscle that muscle
activation did indeed go up and often
times the synergis activation would go
down which is cool because that has
implications for injury prevention and
also back then you know 10 years back
people would say hypertrophy is about
Force production tension you're going to
have more tension when you produce more
total force and these studies show that
you produce greater force when you focus
externally so therefore it's better for
hypertrophy but the problem with that
line of research is they're looking at
Ground reaction force you know do a
squat or a deadlift and you will produce
greater force but that's ground reaction
force okay that's you lift heavier
weight you put more Force into the
ground but that does not equal muscle
Force okay there's a lot of muscles
involved in the deadlift a lot of
muscles involved in the squat as well so
just because you lifted more weight it
does not mean that you used your glutes
to a greater degree you know you could
have squatted more weight because you
used your quads more you had better
timing of muscle activation that led to
the greatest amount of weight being
lifted and one of the leading authors on
this line of research her name is Dr
Gabriel wolf she's published more
studies on attentional Focus than anyone
she has this constrained action
hypothesis that indicates that you know
with something involving performance
when you focus on something external on
something in the environment your body
activates the precise motor units in the
right combination in the different
muscles that maximizes performance so
your body has a natural way of doing
things by focusing externally your
neuromuscular system is going to work
perfectly to execute that task whereas
if you focus on one of the muscles
you're going to overactivate that muscle
and maybe screw up the timing and it's
going to interfere with performance and
basically what we're finding is yes that
is true you don't want to use the Mind
muscle connection when you're doing
something performance related if you're
focus on hypertrophy then you do want to
focus internally at least some of the
times another reason for utilizing the
Mind muscle connection is that every
bodybuilder swears by it you constantly
hear bodybuilders say you know I never
felt my pecs in a bench press until I
really learned to bench like a
bodybuilder and use my pecs I've had
clients who don't feel their glutes much
in a hip thrust initially and then after
a couple months their glutes burn so bad
it brings tears to their eyes I remember
when I first first started lifting at 15
years old I didn't know how to flex my
lats I would sit there in the mirror and
I'd be like you know trying to contract
my lats it took me a while to figure out
how to flex them I remember my delts I
was like how can I what pose makes me
activate my deltoids and I would just
sit there in the mirror flexing and
looking at myself in the mirror and
flexing different muscles and I believe
that helped my performance in the long
run cuz if I'm doing a lat pull down and
I can't contract my lats how am I going
to do it properly in the book super
training Dr CIF called it loadless
training that's flexing and posing right
and there are a couple of studies that
show that you know just flexing and
posing do in fact grow muscle and one
study indicates that it packs on muscle
just as effectively as dumbbells do so
now I've presented evidence in support
of the Mind muscle connection I'm going
to tell you why I still favor
Progressive overload Progressive
overload especially on compound
movements is so effective because you're
activating a lot of different muscles
and I think people under estimate all
these little muscles you know check out
someone's back development you know you
think oh that's all lats coming up no
back here is the Terry's major and minor
and they're big muscles you know there's
also the supraspinatus and you look at a
very welldeveloped back and you see
those muscles contribute a lot to the
overall back development you know
speaking of the back you've got the
Erectors underneath you know you've got
the lats you've also have the the traps
which are diamond shaped you've got the
upper mid and lower portion and the
rhomboids so if you're just trying to
squeeze the weight and feel a certain
muscle you're not going to get as strong
over time and it's going to limit your
performance and the weight that you
could be using now I've definitely seen
really Jack dudes at the gym who just do
mind muscle connection stuff you know
you see them like doing just body weight
dips but squeezing and really focusing
on the movement and you know you see
them doing curls with light dumbbells
but they're just squeezing using just
perfect form and like wow that guy's
using such lightweight but he's jacked
but you see so many more instances where
guys are just freakishly strong and they
have a very well-developed physique I
rarely see a guy who can do a weighted
chin up with 100 lb military press 200
lb bench press 300 lb squat 400 lb
deadlift 500 lb and hip thrust 600 lb
and have a lackluster physique I'm sure
you can find someone out there but it's
rare because when you do a chin up
you're working the lats you're working
the forearms you're working the biceps
the chin-up is one of the best ab
exercises in existence surprisingly when
you do military press you know you're
not just working the delts well you're
also working the triceps you're working
the upper back musculature bench press
is obviously going to work the pecs the
front delts the triceps squats are going
to work the Erectors they're going to
work the glutes the quads deadlifts are
going to work you know the hamstrings
the glutes the quads
the whole back musculature the forearms
and hip thrusts are going to work the
glutes really well but also the
hamstrings and quads but also all the
little muscles that get worked just by
moving heavy heavy weight around and
that adds up and that's what contributes
to Twin number two being overall leaner
than twin number one so that's why I
believe that Progressive overload is
more important than the Mind muscle
connection however this whole video is
nonsense because it's What's called the
black or white f policy luckily in
strength training you don't have to do
one or the other you do them both and I
always say in my seminars there's two
necessary paths to maximize hypertrophy
you know you have the progressive
overload path and the mind muscle
connection path and they're both
necessary think of the yin and the Yang
you know you got to have them both one
without the other will lead to
suboptimal gains so to wrap this up if I
had to pick one I would choose setting
PRS and getting stronger but in the real
world you don't have to to choose
between the two you would do them both
so what I recommend is the first
exercise of the day go for Progressive
over do heavier weight lower rep ranges
but then towards the end of the workout
more single joint exercises more EXC
where you just go lighter and really
squeeze the muscle and feel the burn so
instead this video should involve
triplets you know triplet one just does
my muscle connection triplet two does
Progressive overload triplet 3 does both
and he ends up being the most ripped and
jacked all right that's a wrap I hope
you enjoy the video please make sure
you're subscribed to my channel
definitely hit like if you appreciate
the content and please leave me a
message let me know how I'm doing I have
a lot of good content planned for the
rest of 2022 thank you for watching this
video